William Dunn MD Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
William Dunn MD Papers
1946 - 1955
William Dunn was chief of the Out Patient Department at the Payne Whitney Psychiatric Clinic of New York Hospital. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
.84 linear feet (2 boxes)
Dunn, William H., 1898-1955
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1955.0001
Gift of Oskar Diethelm, 1955.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
William H. Dunn, M.D. was born on April 13, 1898 in Scottsville, New York. He received his Bachelor’s degree from the University of Rochester in 1923 and his M.D. from Harvard Medical School in 1927. He was appointed Assistant Physician at Bloomingdale Hospital in 1929. He served as Assistant and then Associate Attending Psychiatrist at New York Hospital. Dunn also served as Chief of the Outpatient Department of the Payne Whitney Clinic and taught at Cornell University Medical College.
Dunn was a consultant at the post-World War II crime trials at Nuremberg, Germany. During the war, Dr. Dunn was a lieutenant colonel in the Army Medical Corps, serving in the United States and in the Southwest Pacific, and winning the Legion of Merit. Some of his publications pertain to psychiatric problems in the Armed Forces and to the Nuremberg trial. He died in February 1955 in New York City.
Dunn, William H., 1898-1955; Payne Whitney Psychiatric Clinic; World War, 1939-1945; American Psychiatric Association
The William H. Dunn Papers consist of a diverse assortment of papers spanning the years 1946-1954. Dunn’s professional correspondence consists of letters of recommendation for colleagues and students along with other matters. A grouping of papers prepared for the International Congress on Mental Health which took place in London in August 1948 is included in the collection. Under the stimulus of Dr. Frank Fremont-Smith of the Josiah Macy Foundation, a Preparatory Commission made a study of the Nazi hierarchy, based particularly on material accumulated in the Nuremberg prison, in an effort to discover possible implications for world mental hygiene. Drs. Margaret Mead and William Dunn were members, as were Drs. Richard M. Brickner, John Frosch, and G. M. Gilbert. These papers consist of correspondence among the various planners, and drafts of papers dealing with guilt and authoritarian trends in German culture, aggression, and studies of German prisoners of war in the United States. Dunn served as associate editor of the Bulletin of the American Psychoanalytic Association and resigned in December 1951 due to ill health. Folders pertaining to the Association contain additional recommendations for colleagues and a report of the Ad Hoc Committee on Institutes and Societies of the Committee on Affiliate Societies.
Background data for the Preparatory Commission and summary reports for a Conference on Psychiatric Education held at Cornell University in Ithaca on June 21-27, 1951 are also included. The conference was organized and conducted by the American Psychiatric Association and the Association of American Medical Colleges. A published report of this conference can be found in Psychiatry and Medical Education, American Psychiatric Association, Washington, D.C. 1952. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
- No series
  - Biographical Information, c. 1950 - 1955 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence A – E, 1948 - 1955 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence F – L, 1946 - 1954 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence M, 1946 - 1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence N – R, 1946 - 1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence S – T, 1947 - 1954 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence W – Z, 1946 - 1954 (Box 1)
  - Obituary of Dr. Ross McClure Chapman, 1948 (Box 1)
  - International Congress on Mental Health with correspondence re: Preparatory Commission and and guilt and authoritarian trends in German culture, 1947 - 1948 (Box 1)
  - International Congress on Mental Health, “The Problem of German Authoritarianism and Aggression” report and drafts, 1947 (Box 1)
  - International Congress on Mental Health Preparatory Commission, 1947 - 1948 (Box 1)
  - American Psychoanalytic Association, 1948 - 1952 (Box 1)
  - American Psychoanalytic Association Ad Hoc Committee on Relationship of Institutes and Societies of the Committee on Affiliate Societies, 1954 (Box 1)
  - “A Program Dealing with the Interrelationship of Psychiatry and Religion at Union Theological Seminary” preliminary draft, Undated (Box 2)
  - American Psychiatric Association Dunn - Chairman, Committee on Membership, 1949 - 1950; 1954 (Box 2)
  - U.S. War Department, 1946 - 1952 (Box 2)
  - Conference on Psychiatric Education, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Conference on Psychiatric Education, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Conference on Psychiatric Education “The Sociological Background Social Change and Emotional Problems”, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Conference on Psychiatric Education “Anxiety and its Relation to the Culture Pattern and Personality Development Among Primitive People”, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Conference on Psychiatric Education summaries of group discussions, etc., 1951 (Box 2)
  - Conference on Psychiatric Education summary reports, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, c. 1947 - c. 1953 (Box 2)